okay
uh we were going through the seven
Diamond visions and uh besides the one
that Winston had a few years ago
uh to buy this
property uh what was it we finished two
I think what's the third one no we only
finished
one what's the second
one yeah d
okay I'll just put it up here so you
remember what we're talking about is
that okay for your camera yeah
say uh CH means Dharma means ratna uh
jeel so d
[Music]
Davido or
guo Mr
Brian result Refuge or cause of
Refuge
uh it's it's a result Refuge when you're
refering to yourself yeah going for
Refuge to the Dharma Jewel that you're
going to achieve that's uh he did all
Peno but um the first uh three of the
seven Diamond visions are referring to
the three Jews but with reference to
what you're going to become yourself
right so result Refuge right going
to refuge in the result is how I
remember it in what I'm going to become
okay so tonight we're going to talk
about how you will become one of the
three refugees actually you become
the win two of the three
refugees when you see him to when
emptiness directly okay when you see the
moment you see emptiness directly you
become the which which two of the three
jewels that's easy become the DH jeel
and the S yeah dhad jeel and S jeel okay
you become and I I just always thought
it was cool because there's still even
with all the political problems that
Buddhists have in the world there's
still millions of Buddhists who get up
every morning and say you know Buddha
Buddha
[Music]
yeah and then uh it's kind of cool to
think that when you reach that then
they'll be whether they know it or not
they're going to Refuge to you uh so
it's kind of cool but
um your your CH coin Joe is a state of
mind these are things in your own mind
okay certain levels that you've reached
in your own mind and as we're going to
see later today it's two of the four
so-called Noble AR truths okay you get
two of the Four Noble Truth in your mind
and that makes you CH Chong okay the
direct perception of emptiness also
means that you have two of the Four
Noble Truths in your own mind so I
thought it might be good to go over the
four noble truths while we're at it the
four ARA truths
because uh they come in the fourth
chapter of the UT Tantra so what I did
was I just stole that whole section out
of the fourth chapter and brought it to
the first chapter so we're going to do a
a review of the four truths and then
we're going to see how you become two of
them or how you achieve two of them to
become the Jewel of the Dharma okay so I
thought we'd go over the four truth it's
a very very famous verse from the utar
Tantra like I'm trying to pick the 10
most famous verses from the utar Tantra
the ones that you'll hear all the time
in the debate ground and things like
that
um and and the more I do of this kind of
uh work I see that the L Rim is based
heavily on the utar Tantra although it
doesn't mention it much okay so I think
um you'll recognize a lot of what I'm
going to say even now uh but now you
know where it comes from okay so the
we're going to discuss the first of the
four ARA truths okay called ARA truths
because
Mercedes good in in the hours following
the direct perception of emptiness and
Arya has uh four or you can call it four
extraordinary realizations four groups
of extraordinary realizations consisting
of
16 sub realizations consisting of lots
of others realizations but anyway you
can group them all into four and those
are called the four ar your truths
because an AR is someone who has seen
emptiness directly so Noble is a
mistranslation noble is a bad
translation of the Sanskrit word ARA or
Paka in tibetan um so which is the first
of the Four Noble Truths uh David Stone
suffering
sure that's the way to stop again you
sure first of the four first of for AR
truth
yeah I don't know if it's in course
number two uh is there any other order
to
fores I mean traditional order is what
you said which is suffering you see
suffering then you want to
see you want to find out suffering cause
of suffering what caus iter how to you
want to see if you can end it and then
you want to see how to end it so that's
what we call like uh CA that's what we
call realization order okay you see that
the world is suffering you want to
figure out why it's happening you decide
that you could stop it and then you
figure out how to stop it but there's
also what they call the actual order do
you know which is what the order in
which they really
occur yeah first the cause of
suffering then suffering itself
then follow path then you follow the
path and then you get to the end so
there's two there's a debate in the
scriptures you know which order you
going to follow tonight we're following
Mr stumps order okay so it's uh first
would be
what
yeah yeah
it's a k right
say
[Music]
wait and and I think and it's might it's
like a review for most of you but you
know that four truths doesn't mean a
principle okay it doesn't mean like the
four principles or something like that
it means four realities four real things
like like this is doing on them
this is the truth of suffering okay my
body is the truth of suffering this is
the truth of suffering this is the truth
of suffering uh everything in a normal
person's world is the truth of suffering
because it's been created by their own
Karma and negative emotions claas okay
so it's not like the truth of suffering
is a principle it's a it's a fact in the
sense of the things which constitute
that fact so it's not just going around
saying everything is suffering that's
true and that's a truth but that's not
what dunal Dema is dunal DBA is all the
stuff which is actually suffering which
is everything which has been produced by
negative emotions and Karma Bad Karma
okay
uh then in thear Tantra in the fourth
chapter I'm skipping to the fourth
chapter uh my tra
says for
say
n uh May means CH had it this
afternoon I knew
[Music]
this disease illness sickness okay this
KN is what we call equational sentence
which means is in it just means it's a
pointer you know sickness I mean in
English you just point your finger but
in Sanskrit and Tibetan it's the is
sickness is the sh sh what's
sh it's a name of a tobet newspaper in
DMS
sh which means what Noble things they
call the newspaper Noble things you know
uh things to know about but what it
means here is this JW is the imperative
you must grasp suffering you must grasp
that you have that disease okay must
grasp the disease okay
um and I think uh when you're teaching
in
the in the Muse what's it called what's
the fancy name of that YMCA uh Muse two
son School two son Center for theart
Center for the
Arts uh okay which it is kind of like
that but anyway uh when you're teaching
people I think that's kind of where I
put the four a CHS at the beginning of
this lesson although you've already had
them I think especially if people walk
in or new people from out of town or
something like that you got to be able
to go over the four IU before you get
into why two of them are the Dharma
Jewel okay so you got to have the four
arot truths on your fingertips like that
and the way the utar Tantra presents the
four eye of truths is just by saying
look you got to understand that you're
in trouble you have to grasp that
there's a problem here and
and that's the big Crux for 99% of the
people you know I can tell you a horror
story for every person in this room you
know the ones that I know personally the
ones who stuck it out the ones who've
made it here the ones who are very clear
on what they want to do and the ones who
are very clear about their practice and
everything else with every single one of
them there's been some kind of disaster
like they got the wakeup call 10 years
ago 5 years ago 20 years ago uh some
usually a death
but sometimes an accident or an illness
or something like that and the first AA
truth is just you got to understand that
this is happening you must understand
that this is going on when you see
emptiness directly and you come out then
part of the day is spent grasping how
hopeless everything is for almost
everybody you know that everything is
hopeless uh the odds of really pulling
off in this life of pulling off the
Buddhist in this life all the way up to
ZM and then beyond higher tantric
practice it's almost impossible it's
almost totally
impossible
so I mean if you really grasp how
impossible it was just the world would
make you crazy it was it's as if the
World Trade Center thing was happening
every half hour everywhere you know like
people got a little taste of it I saw
the video they sent me a video from New
York City
of some of our students and they all
have this to me you know not having been
there not having seen i' I still haven't
seen any of the videos or the pictures
I've just heard things and but to see
their faces I can feel it I can see it
in their faces you know and this is like
a couple years later right but I can see
some kind of a doubt or some kind of a
something broken in their faces I don't
know if you can see it cuz you in a way
you had the same experience you see
we didn't we were just sitting there and
we didn't but to see their faces is very
sad in a way and I think um the the you
know obviously the increased interest in
religion all religions in this country
is a direct result I mean sh somebody
has grasped the disease somebody has
grasped what's really going on and I
think again one of the things about
retreat was um realizing how vulnerable
you are realizing how little
uh security we all have because in a
retreat you're purposely putting
yourself into a place of no
security uh to get straight down to the
bottom of your mind and people ask me
why did you pick Arizona why did you
pick such a hot place why did you stay
in such a crummy YT you know why did you
blah blah blah uh with rattlesnakes all
around you know well the point is to I
mean really if you get really serious
about Retreat I'm not suggesting it
immediately for everybody but when
you're up to a certain level you should
expose yourself to a lack of
security and then you get straight down
to what's real and that's that we're all
sick we all have some disease and if we
don't act quickly then there's no chance
so you guys are faced I think the most
important thing you have to say to
people maybe who walk into your class in
Tucson is to is is to get them to feel
this statement by mraa you know that you
must grasp that there's a problem and
that we have very little time to deal
with
it and then coming out our Retreat you
know we're on the web all day we're
using computers all day we spend all day
trying to get our computers to work on
the web and then we don't have time to
do anything else but that's supposed to
be important somehow and saving us time
somehow you know it's very funny I mean
away from it for three years you can see
it's kind of ridiculous I'm sure in 3
months I'll think it's a very important
thing but um uh or maybe three days but
uh it's really funny you don't we don't
have time to do much of that I mean we
have to do a certain amount to get
readings out and stuff like that but but
on the whole there's no time for those
things we don't have time for those
things it's just study what you need to
study serve others but make sure your
practice is going well make sure you do
what you can do to see emptiness and
then the rest is
Superfluous so you have to know about
the disease
I think very important
to you have to talk about that to the
people you teach in
October because that's really what
that's really why any single person
walks in at down at the bottom there's
some kind of feeling that something's
wrong
okay for
say means
everything Jun means comes from and kjun
means the source of all things the
source deba means truth truth of the
source of suffering and uh I put all
these in the in the Sanskrit also but
I'm not going to do it cuz we don't have
time so if you want to know the Sanskrit
Chris will go over with you on Saturday
but the uh Sanskrit here is het which
just means cause cause of suffering the
truth of the
cause for
say
[Music]
n n
means sickness key means
of g means
cause KN here means
is bang means you must eliminate it you
must stop it you must cut off the cause
of
suffering I always think of it like uh
you know sometimes when you're taking a
shower which is such a nice thing uh and
you hit the water thing and you turn off
the cold water and then suddenly it's
like 200° hot water and uh there's two
approaches you can take then you know
one is you can take your hand and hold
it up to the head of the shower and try
to stop the water and you'll just burn
yourself you know and the other is you
know if you can think it's just to turn
it off and that's the difference between
nay and and naked you you know we don't
try to stop
suffering as it comes out it's too late
it's too late okay you got to get to the
source bang that's the beauty of
Buddhism I mean that's the
great secret of Lord Buddha's approach
you know you don't try to stop events
after they're already happening it's too
late it's what we call hard concrete
right it's too late concrete's already
hard and you know you've been the whole
world is trying to deal with their
current Pain by using
methods that would address it in the
current moment and they fail every
single one
fails the whole world is trying to
achieve some kind of minimum Comfort
before they die right and they're trying
to work in such a way that whatever they
do right at this moment would stop what
they don't like at this moment and
that's impossible according to Buddhism
that's just impossible you have to go to
the source you have to stop the source
and then slowly the the suffering will
stop
okay the and there's a sort of a tracing
back to the source right you go to the
person you met at work that you don't
like and then you trace it back
to some kind of negative Karma that
you're collecting and then you trace
that back to some wrong way in which
you're looking at things and then you
trace that back to the the habit of
looking like that and then you trace
that back to the seed that you came into
this
this life with looking at things that
way yeah uh we talked about yoga Sutra M
tra six steps and we talked about it in
um lots of times before that right
course 12 yeah so to me it's one of the
sweetest teachings of all time right but
anyway you have to get rid of the cause
it's which means according to Buddhism
to try to reason or to try to discuss it
with a person who's causing you trouble
at work just doesn't
work trying to confront them or trying
to reconcile with them the two choices
right neither one works
anyway and that's proven by the fact
that doesn't always work well they don't
always work you know this reconciliation
doesn't always work and confrontation
doesn't always work you know whenever
you confront and doesn't work you think
maybe reconciliation would have worked
whenever try reconciliation that doesn't
work you thought that maybe confronting
would have worked but the fact is that
neither one is a is a cause neither one
is addressing the cause so it doesn't
work if you were having trouble with
someone at work the wisest thing would
be to just try to be more kind to
everybody and specifically to the person
you're having trouble with which is the
whole message of say Christianity but it
all got lost you know the whole idea is
all mixed up you know but the the idea
is that it's not just to turn the other
cheek because it's Noble it's that if
you refuse to respond to violence with
violence you cut off future violence
like turning off the the
shower so that's addressing the cost you
must eliminate the cost
okay is it
go
yeah for
and I also wanted to say those of you
who teach in Tucson you got
to I think it might be wise G to to find
out the background of the people coming
and try to group them into like have you
taken two class courses ACI or less have
you taken two to five have you and try
to group them because how much foreign
language you lay on people depends on I
mean you need enough to impress them and
not so much that you confuse them and
lose them
so but then you could bore that really
the ones who've been through a lot get
bored if you don't throw it in so you
got to I think we might have to group
them people because there'll be a wide
variety it's like teaching fifth grade
to senior in high school in the same
group you know and so anyway Goen means
the truth of stopping it they call it
sensation I don't like a word that long
say well it's not so long but uh
it's not good to useong words in
anything when you're explaining but uh
truth of sensation truth of stopping the
suffering putting an end to the
suffering go means to stop Den means the
truth okay and it says
[Music]
here for
say to to means uh feel good name means
uh condition day name means health
health
KN means is top means something we want
to attain we want to get
okay you have to go
after Health if you're sick you have to
go after Health if you're
sick in Buddhism and I
repeat
uh the goal is not uh to feel good for a
while the goal is not to be more calfor
for a while the goal is not to be more
friendly just to be more friendly you
know the goal is not to be able to cope
with life better as it kills you okay
and I'm very I keep repeating that
probably till I die and uh I just want
to drill it in one more time I mean if
we start a center in Tucson for example
which we will uh as we start this
University which we have
uh retreat center and other activities
as we do the class I mean it has to be
in the back of your mind that what's
your offering people is is the chance
not to die and and then when I say that
I sometimes friends look at me and they
look at me like that uh sometimes I feel
like a Christian preacher and they're
talking in metaphor you know like yeah
you'll still get old and ugly and
wrinkled and die but after that the Lord
has something waiting for you you know
that's not what would talking about I
mean and then sometimes when I say oh
you can have eternal life you know
people
like uh they heard that
before but but it is truly that you
would transform that uh with a
gradual patient determined practice
culminating in a lot of retreat and a
lot of study of the higher teachings
especially to do with your inner body
then you would actually change your your
whole being would
change and you would become a being who
is not uh
mortal and then people ask me well would
you just get more and more wrinkly you
know and it's not like that your body
changes into pure light and that is the
way we were meant to be and that's the
way my tray is that's how the
description goes after the dog popped
out of sight for a sa which a reading
you'll probably get sooner or later I
think we send it possibly out by email
or something but I think I can maybe
finish it by Sunday morning or something
but I don't know uh the first reading
which is really nice uh but the point is
that you din are made of a different
substance You're Made Of L and that's
the goal and that's why we work up from
the 18 courses then through the tant
courses 18 tant courses and the goal is
that you just change so we want that
kind of Health that's the goal and
you're going to see a very beautiful
quot by m Saturday
Saturday yeah uh where he states that
again very clearly and I like it it's a
very famous uh quotation in the debate
ground
uh people who have seen emptiness have
cut off from its root the source of
death and and I like that you don't see
it it gets lost in modern Buddhist
presentations I think I mean even if the
presentation is Tibetan Buddhist even if
it's founded in the traditional
scriptures you don't actually hear
people saying look if you really work on
this hard your body will change into
light and you don't have to work that's
the end of the process and then you can
serve all living beings automatically
spontaneously I think it's important to
keep repeating it to people uh
say lumon l l l l l means path Den means
truth of the path truth of the path to
the end of
suff I mean and the most important one
is just the direct perception emptiness
that's is the classic lambden okay that
is the classic
lden for
say
many men means do you know huh medicine
okay like menla house
right okay KN means ear
this spelling with the S head letter
those of you who are studying tetan
which is
unusual means to be relied upon or to be
used like medicine or food or a llama
the same
verb uh to be relied
upon in this case to be taken you have
to take the medicine
okay so to go over the four parts of his
sickness metaphor what's the first
part you need to know you're sick you
got to get it that you're sick okay how
many people do you know who have a
serious disease who just refuse to admit
it you know like I'll be all right the
funniest thing I mean the saddest thing
you hear is I'll fight this thing come
on what are you talking about fight this
thing you know what are you going to do
you
know you're going to Shell out money to
any kind of crazy cure you can and then
you're going to die anyway you know
that's a i it drives me crazy when I
hear people I'm GNA fight this thing you
know I got cancer so maybe you better
study hard meditate hard I'll fight this
thing you know come on what's that mean
you know uh
second comes from the source no but what
was the statement my said you
gotta you must eliminate cut off causes
you got to cut it off you got to turn it
off turn off the source at the source
okay gets to be a certain point in an
illness that it's too late okay even if
you took yourself to his Holiness and he
said okay I'll give up all my other work
and I'll just teach you and uh you went
to dmal and said oh don't worry I'll
take care of you got cancer okay just do
what I say you know do this meditation L
then uh take these vows then uh get
these initiations then uh go through
these visualizations then achieve that
in your real life then uh do this Zod
stuff and then uh work on your inner
channels and chakras and then you know I
can take care of you it's too late it's
too late you know I mean even if you had
this hoess there and he had nothing else
to do it's too late it's just too
late uh so you got to cut it off at the
source third
one
TR to stop truth
sensation yeah uh feel good reach your
10 yeah get heal get health get healthy
get healthy
how yeah take the medicine okay so it
goes in the flow like that you got to
understand you're sick come on you got
to understand something terrible is
happening okay all the every moment of
your
life then you you have to figure out
what's causing it then you have
to get health and you have to find out
how to do that you have to take the
medicine okay and the process is long
and
hard and you have to start and you have
to put some hard work into it I was
reading the statements by the retreats
to the newspaper reporter and it was all
like I just figured out I'm just
starting you know after 3 years I
decided I've got a good start you know
and it's like that it's hard it's hard
you have to work hard okay
uh now the point is about about the
reason we brought this
up is that this are your
truth of the
path and this are your truth of shutting
off the shower turning off the shower
what do you call it thing
knob faucet shutting off the faucet and
uh and this one Lumen how to shut up you
know reach out and turn your hand okay
the way
and that cutting it off those two are
the Dharma Jewel those two in the mind
of a person who has seen emptiness
directly are the Dharma Jewel that is
the Dharma Jewel okay and hopefully if
they're bodh sappa it' be good too throw
that in okay all right those two are the
Dharma Jewel now I got a question for
you maybe uh Earl he
which one comes first gden or
lambden lden yeah I mean normally you
practice the path and
then yeah how about if I ask
you which comes first Buddha Jewel or
Dharma
Jewel especially in our context here of
the seven Diamond Visions right this in
this context of Earl the future Buddha
and by the way they won't call you Earl
that's another
story but your buddhahood and your
Buddha the Buddha Jewel that you will be
if you're not already and the Buddha
Jewel that the Dharma Jewel that you
will attain if you haven't already which
comes
first why because you see the during the
direct perception of an have direct
realization of the DH that's nice
realization
that's nice that's not bad that's not a
bad answer but do you become the Buddha
Jewel when you see an this directly no
yeah that's the only jewel you don't
become when you say to this directly
right you become the other
two so if I want to say in which order
do you become the the Buddha Jewel and
the Dharma Jewel which comes
first when you become
it the
D yeah you become dharm Jewel first at
path of seeing right or at least you
attain it in your mind the path which is
the direct perception of emptiness and
Sensations but do you attain Sensations
when you see anything this directly like
what sensation of what doub path yeah
you can't doubt the path ever again and
mainly one other
one believing in suff and things
intellectually okay so you do achieve a
truth of sensation and truth of the PA
they come first and then later much
later you become the Buddha jeel right
fully enlightened
being now let's take it from the point
of view of
uh that's
tough but in terms of the we talked
about the Dharma jeel your ear's Dharma
Jewel in terms of the Dharma teachings
you would give after you became
enlightened right
we talked of it that way we talked about
it in terms of Boda the first three
Diamond like Visions can be explained in
terms of bod how
why it's like a
wish that's
true but but there's a process there
which is what I want
to so I can so I can
create other s Jews right in that case
which comes first
if you say I want to become a fully
enlightened being so I can read
everybody's minds and know exactly what
to teach them so that I can most quickly
lead them to see emptiness directly
Buddha Dharma
s in that case which comes
first you're own become Buddha you
become a Buddha first so Buddha comes
first then you speak dhad and then you
create a sa of people who have seen EMP
directly because of Earl's teachings as
a Buddha okay
G of J says you can think of it that way
you know if someone comes up to you and
asks you which comes first Buddha jeel
dhel s you can say well in terms of
progression of what I'd like to see
happen which is the bodh part I'd like
to become in line so I can give my own
fantastic teaching Sutra and Tantra in
the world that I'm dealing with planets
that I'm on so that people can become
SEL they can see emptiness directly
but now he oh we're not done
yet but if you define the Dharma
Jewel as the ultimate
sensation truth of sensation and the
ultimate truth of the path in a being's
mind in your own mind then which comes
first Buddha jeel or DH jeel D yeah the
ultimate
version of these two truths in in Earl's
mind is going to happen
when ultimate
version yeah which means cessation which
means got rid of every problem
everything at buddhahood so which comes
first Buddha je or D je gosip J is very
concerned about
this he says from a developmental point
of view I want to become a Buddha then
later I'll be able to teach and then
later people will get to see emptiness
because of me but if you think of dharm
jeel as the path and the sensations in
your own mind which is the real Dharma
jeel right the ultimate version of that
which comes first Buddha Jewel or Dharma
jeel yeah neither it comes
simultaneously okay then g j says
uh it's like saying and it comes across
better in tibetan and Sanskrit than it
does in English but here here we go uh
opening her mouth she
sleeps opening her mouth she
sleeps okay which came
first opening her mouth or
sleeping
in and there's a trick with the Nay
which is a big deal in Sanskrit and
Tibetan grammar it means it can mean
first she
yawned and then she fell asleep see
opening her mouth she
slept okay but it could just
mean she sleeps with you know she sleeps
with her mouth open okay you see what I
mean
and and he says that's a good metaphor
for how people understand this process
like if you say opening her mouth she
sleeps maybe 75% of people will take it
as she yawns so she went to
bed but then the 25% will get it she was
sleeping with her mouth open
meaning most people think in terms of
progression Buddha I'm going to get a
enlightened so I can teach the Dharma is
that the Dharma
Jewel deceptive D who said that alist
it's oh Winston it's the fake Dharma Jew
it's apparent Dharma Jewel that's not
the real Dharma okay Talking Words books
not the real Dharma right so that's
that's you can say that kind of order
but it's not really so relevant what's
the real Dharma
jeel yeah it's realizations in your own
mind and the permanent getting rid of
bad stuff in your own being that you
achiev because of those realizations
called Truth or sensation okay so don't
think of Truth or sensation just in in
terms of uh not
dying it also means
like like there's a place even be when
you understand emptiness fairly well at
the second path path of preparation
there comes a point at which you can no
longer
what impossible to take a birth in the
lower Realms I mean if nothing else
matters in this life you should just
kick ass on the ACI courses and try to
get to the intellectual understanding
emptiness that would get you over that
level then you could sort of relax a bit
you know I mean like I'm not going to be
in the hell Realms anymore just
impossible I'm not going to the hell
Realms I'm not going to an animal realm
like you can be nervous when you die you
know you might be born in this country
or that country or this planet or that
planet but you know you're not going to
be born in a bad place you know you're
not going to be really born in a in a
really hellish place we saw uh what was
that our first DVD on our computer
uh which is why everyone's so grumpy
because they stayed up late uh it was
Matrix
uh Matrix cartoons or something like
that I don't know but uh there was one
of these horrible beings coming up like
billions and billions out of this hell
plateau and there you could see like a
funnel coming up and that just that's
what the hell RS look like like the guy
who did that
animation was was uh calling on a seed
in his own mind for something he has
experienced countless times it's not
just some stupid thing that somebody
made up it's a he's drawing he's
siphoning images out of actual
experiences that he went through
countless times and when you see a movie
Once you know everything you know you
can
see former life images coming up in
people animators Minds as they think
they're creating but they're just
linking into some experience they've had
countless times and they are able to
render it with great uh
accuracy uh I think it's the third one
if you're
interested the third little cartoon but
anyway you won't have to go through like
something like that if you achieve a
Goen if you achieve a Goen if you just
get to a certain level of understanding
that all the problems you run into in
the world are coming from me you know
and it's weird you know we can be a
group of us sitting around all afternoon
working together and all just losing
that understanding constantly you know
like minor irritation at another person
and you're just losing it you're just
losing it you thinking oh other person
other person other person they irritate
me they doing something to me you know
like even in a group of people who have
been through it for 10 15
years you know all of us in an afternoon
we're like interacting and then there's
this 98% level of them you know it's not
like it's me who's caused all this you
know
and if you can get past
that at a certain intellectual level
then you don't have to S you don't have
to go to a lower realm anymore you can
die peacefully you know I mean so you
can practice it anytime
anywhere be better to have a difficult
place to practice it you know like this
is a little not very
conducive place cuz everyone's
practicing you know what I mean you mean
ideally would be to have uh someplace
where people didn't know anything about
that and then they really attack you
nicely
and bother you nicely and and there's no
hint of maybe it's our fault you know
what I mean that would be the best place
to stay I think we'll still build
diamond mountain
they have a few
people uh I wanted to talk about the
tooth of sensation in a little bit of
detail okay stopping stopping shutting
it off reaching out and no that's just
turning off the faucet right turning off
the faucet
[Music]
and it has two parts what I wanted to
say it has the two same Parts as we
talked about with the body of a Buddha
with the Essence body of a Buddha those
of you who had a discussion with someone
else about the class probably remember
this okay because it was two of the
qualities on the um taking care of
yourself sign which were what natural
and achieved Purity yeah nice natural
and achieved Purity if you take the
essence body of abuna of the
dharmakaya you could divide it into the
part which has always been pure by
nature natural purity and then there's
the part which has become pure through a
process okay and we're going to have
that same division with this okay with
this truth of sensation okay
um and again the natural
purity just has to do with your natural
emptiness the emptiness that you've
always
had okay
emptiness achieve Purity in this sense
has a little bit different meaning and
I'm going to go through
that oh I'm
sorry he's got three qualities of
natural purity so I'm going to give you
those okay three call these in natural
purity uh
J uh G of J it's in a verse by mraa and
G of J is depending on A's commentary
and he's he's taking it out for us and
breaking it out because you can't see it
in the utar Tantra it's thear Tantra
would just have code words and then if
you read the master of s commentary you
get the meaning and then G of is
clarifying it further and then our
textbook writers from each of the great
monasteries turned it into a pedagogical
presentation you know which is very
powerful and I'm hoping to do some of
that uh when we get to Rick especially
come when we get to come I think I'll
throw in like six or seven debates from
the because that's how you really
understand it if you understand the
debate you understand gsub J then you
can understand ARA then you can
understand my train and it really goes
like that uh so
uh number one
[Music]
say Okay dualism is at the root of all
the problems okay and uh
it doesn't mean what Alis
dualism it doesn't mean that
the the subject perceiver and the
perceived object
are they typically one of one thing yeah
it doesn't mean that okay it doesn't
mean that somehow you melt into the
popcorn that you're looking at okay it
doesn't mean that and and then there is
a a human urge there's an merge within
the human
being to
overcome uh discursive thought you know
like I spoke to a heroin addict in New
York one time and I said you know and he
was like very apologetic for being a
heroin addict and I said it's not my
business but I'm curious why you know
what drives you to take it you know and
he says if I could just stop the
thoughts in my own mind that's all I
want you know like what you get during
sleep
the kind of refreshing you get during
sleep I never get that I can't get it
even when I'm asleep so I use heroin to
try to shut shut up my mind so that's
all that's all I and I worked for like a
couple hours and then it comes back
again you know but he said just that
feeling of having your own thoughts shut
up and you know if you spend three years
in a year you know the same thing you
know you can sit there hour after hour
and hour and you're like trying to shut
up your goddamn mind you know like
you're like like this you know and it's
like singing uh advertising Jingles from
when you were in sixth grade you know
there a uh uhoh Spaghetti O you know
you're like you're like this you know
and you're like and the longer you're in
Retreat the earlier it goes back the
Mind goes back further and further and
then you're like hearing these idiotic
things from first second grade you know
you're like and you can't stop it you
know so there's this human urge to stop
this uh dual feeling of being separate
but that's not how it works I mean
that's not how it works and it's not
that you can shut the mind off you can't
you know it never turns off after you
get in light and the mind continues
right it's just Pleasant okay so what
does this dualism mean
Debbie give me a nice mind only
answer me and the
me and the
pen are not
dual
because yeah essentially it's one part
of the mind I'm looking at something
which I'm projecting we came from the
same kic seed right yeah we came from
the same kic
seed right uh that's a pretty good mind
on the answer okay I'm not separate from
the pen
because we are being driven we're being
spewed forth from the same karmic seed
me the Observer and the observe thing
are being spewed forth from the same
Chic
seene is there any problem with that
presentation why do we say it's my only
presentation only one problem really
it's not much of a problem because
you're considering the seed that is
coming from the selfish yeah there's
this Storehouse Consciousness it's where
the seed lies it's spewing for with me
and the pen to me to look at the
pen uh and then how do I think about
that projector do I take the projector
as being self-existent we talked about
that that's the only problem they have
that's like somehow they get it about me
in the pen but they feel different about
where it's all coming from has material
substance to them yeah what they call
materiality and that's a good point
because it doesn't sound like what it
means did they think that this is your
mind and is that why they're called Mind
only no okay you guys are no fun I got
to find new stuff cannot be perceived by
a mind that still has dualism okay like
if you don't overcome thinking that the
irritating people you met this afternoon
are coming from you you will never see
emptiness directly you will never see
natural
purity of the truth of
sensation directly that's all can't you
can't okay you have to at least get over
that intellectual thing that those those
people who bother me are coming from or
the stress that comes to me is coming
from the outside it's it's coming from
you okay uh if you can't get beyond that
you you won't see the natural
purity second one
cannot be perceived to another and it's
the same thing we talked about with the
uh K yeah Ken sheni Dogman yeah and
other meant two things remember give me
one don't be a d don't be a virtue hog
discursive thought and
cses okay sorry I
was we used to have fights over bills in
the restaurants and checks in the
restaurant New York and The Virtue Pig
would get it and run to the cashier and
pay and the other person wouldn't get a
chance to feed D brother or sister and
anyway cannot be pursued through another
meaning another can either
mean uh discursive perceptions you
know reasoning directly right directly
through words and
Concepts you cannot perceive natural
purity directly so through another
meaning through other ways of thinking
other than what kind of perception
direct direct perception okay which
means logical perception
perceptions based on uh Authority we
talked about them in one of those Quiet
Retreat
teachings was
[Music]
it
okay talk again yeah it's the same thing
really it's the same thing okay can't be
perceived through other ways of
perception meaning words and ideas and
can't be perceived through the
directions to the direct directions of
another person a person who seen
emptiness no matter how much they may
wish to convey it to you can only take
you through the process which would
cause you to see it yourself and cannot
in a 15minute description of what they
saw make you see it okay or we wouldn't
be
here
okay number three
is it different from one who
said is it different from one different
from one is
it well one says it can't be perceived
by a mind that still has rism says can
be perceived only by mind that
is right now there's two ways you could
handle this in debate ground right
somebody
says number one and number three are
mount to the same thing don't
they you say
y okay since you bit
if something is a mind which is free of
Duality uh
sorry if you get rid of Duality do you
get to the mind which is free of
Duality meaning which procees nothing
this directly
right which is to say are there any
states of Mind other than oh yeah there
are yeah lots lots of
things so there are other stuff
so they are not in a uh what they call
it
exclusive contradictory what do they
call it mut mutually exclusive
contradiction meaning if you get rid of
one and you get rid of the other there's
nothing left in the universe you say I
mean is that the
case with uh with these two with with
one and
three yeah right that's what that's what
g j would say uh there's lots of things
that are not dualism which are not free
of dualism the State of Mind free of
dualism you see I
mean but it could be a great debate for
a couple hours uh you could say three
and yeah you could say that maybe okay
anyway the point here I think he's
tending more towards direct perception
of emptiness you know it's one thing to
say you can't see it if you are still
thinking of the person who upset you
this afternoon as being produced outside
you it's another thing to see directly
their emptiness okay that's a big
difference you see I mean I think that's
more what he's getting at I think that's
more what he's getting at because
otherwise I think it would be sort of uh
redundant and he's not a kind of person
to be
redundant um he relates these to the
roote text and you'll see that in the
reading okay he relates these to a
section the utar Tantra that you will
see in the reading when you get it
uh
okay I'm going to stop there for a break
and then after that we're going to
discuss we got one more Purity to cover
what's
that ACH Purity which kind of the more
interesting one right I mean how what is
the process we go through to reach a
truth of cation which is the Purity that
we will be in the end the Purity that we
will get to to the whole Buddhist
practice you know what's exactly are the
steps that we go through to get there
okay to achieve Purity and that's all
we're going to do tonight so have a nice
break relax and maybe get some fresh air
CU a little stuff in
here sayma
Shiva
[Music]
sha yeah
okay
rair a
[Music]
sorry here's the Tibetan which is a
little better it's it's really weird in
the okay I'll just say it you don't have
to
say I bow down to the Sun in the sky
okay uh which is neither that which
neither doesn't exist nor exists nor
both does exist and doesn't exist
nor is anything other than those
two okay I bow down to the Sun in the
sky which neither exists doesn't exist
both does exist and doesn't exist or
neither doesn't exist nor neither does
exist nor doesn't
exist uh and so is beyond thinking
about means you can't talk about it
it must be known by yourself
individually sha which in Sanskrit is
Shiva Shiva uh peace peace so that's you
as the and Jim as that's where he got
the
three that's where he got the three okay
three qualities to do with the natural
sensation and I'll say them again I'll
pull them out and you'll see them you'll
recognize
uh that which is neither not existent or
existent or both or or neither and so
therefore it's beyond allism thinking
about yeah that's the cannot
be uh Perce perceived by a mind that is
still stuck in dualism that's where GJ
got that that's where GJ got that I'll
say it again in this verse from the otar
Tantra um in which he's bowing down to
the Dharma
Jewel which he compares to the sun right
uh he says that thing which is neither
nonexistent nor existent nor both nor
neither I I bow down to that because
it's beyond all
thinking okay so that's where GJ got the
what was it the Oh cannot be perceived
by mind with dualism this still has
dualism what was the next one cannot be
perceived by another yeah and he says
here
which means beyond words Beyond definite
words Beyond
description okay that's where G got that
one must be perceived
individually so we
have can only be perceived by the person
at the path of that's from the yoga C I
think he was heavily linked into patan
or vice versa that's why I think
patanjali's dates are about master suus
dates I think the the whole these whole
things were spreading in India like
crazy at that very moment and you
they're almost like parallel text
running if you really look at them um to
me that's kind of exciting anyway
sangi but what could the individual also
mean known individually
do you
know somebody said they were having a
trouble explaining this
to who said they looked it up in a book
was
that somebody said they were teaching AB
D they had to look it up because I
didn't explain the
difference in theid drama there are two
kinds of sensation
sang Sango means a sensation was a which
is a result of individual perceptions
and SOA means a
which is a result without an individual
perception and then it says the
individual perception means the 16
aspects of the four are your
truths so when they say individually
known it's a it's a code word for seeing
emptiness directly at the PA of seeing
and the aftermath that I think Mercedes
talked about what we call the aftermath
the hours following that perception so
he says can only be known individually
meaning that individual means means by
someone who has gone through the
individual parts of the noble truths and
understands
them so that covers the third one which
is so that's where he got the third one
okay and then shiwa it's peace it's
peace sh Shiva in Sanskrit and it means
natural peace natural Nirvana emptiness
okay now he gets the three qualities of
the achieve Purity the Purity that you
develop over the length of your Buddhist
practice here's how he describes it uh
te it's without
stain
yesi uh it possesses the the light rays
of
wisdom uh it's uh
has to do with removing your attachment
towards all
objects
oops
D
number it it
destroys that attachment and it
destroys anger and it destroys
ignorance the darkness of ignorance and
that's why he Compares this whole Dharma
du thing especially the the truth of
sensation which is what this verse is
about he Compares it to
what the sun I bow down to the sun
wisdom because it
destroys these uh liking
things in a bad way disliking things in
a bad way and ignorance itself which you
can get over if you have knowledge
especially of that which has no sting
what's he talking
about I mean let's break that part
down the last two lines in which he's
bowing down to the sun are about the
achieved
Purity the achieved Purity and he says
look if you want to get to Absolute
Purity you're going to have to let's
think it would take about six steps
you want to get out of the
self-perpetuating
cycle uh returning violence with
violence and creating more violence in
the
future you want to get out of that
self-perpetuating
cycle so you would have to
stop collecting
Karma which itself you know actions
ignor actions are motivated by those
three uh well you can say liking things
and disliking things in an ignorant
way and this is the big selling point
now if I got some new poort tonian in my
breakout session and I wanted to sell
him the D you know it would be this is
the key this is the key you know is it
wrong to
dislike what did I if you had an
irritating person this afternoon is
someone irritated you this
afternoon uh is it wrong to dislike
that your sure it's natural well natural
is a different thing it's certainly
natural but is it wrong to dislike that
no not at all not and that's not
Buddhism that's not Buddhism you're not
supposed to sit there while the World
Trade Center is falling down in your
head and say oh
equinity you know it's not Buddhism it's
not Buddhism you know I mean forget that
and it's a very wrong presentation of
Buddhism it's very very wrong because it
cheats people people out of the real
thing you know it's not some kind of
equinity in the face of of life is very
painful and distasteful and people who
are really irritating that's not the
point uh the point is that it's okay to
dislike
them you should dislike them you should
dislike the world train Center falling
in your head you should dislike a person
who makes you
irritated Dar brother and sister Even In
This Very
Room at 10 minutes ago maybe that's fine
they irritate you they're irritating
that's real that's not unreal but
ignorantly no ignorantly no okay what's
the difference between ignorant liking
and intelligent
disliking with regard to an irritating
person yeah you made it you're making it
as well not making it as it happens but
you made it and if you respond to them
negatively then you could perpetuate
them you perpetuate them
are irritating people irritating yes are
they empty yes are they an illusion yes
are they real yes do they really
irritate yes okay that's what Buddhism
says but it's coming from a seed that
you planted so how the only way to get
rid of them is to stop planting those
seeds does it make them disappear or
change in the next half hour
no okay can you see the connection
directly no and there thus the pain of
the world can you see that by being
irritated at someone this afternoon you
created a thousand more you can't see it
it's invisible you have to take Buddha's
word you have to establish Buddha as a
truthful person and then you have to
establish that it's logical the whole
process of planning seeds through
perceptual processes and then having
that affect how you perceive things or
even create things that you perceive is
very logical but you have to go through
the process logically okay so stop
liking and disliking ignorantly
because when you believe that the
irritating person who's really
irritating didn't come from you then you
fight with them then you then you do
something irritating to them and then
the whole cycle keeps going how can you
stop
that stop uh
thinking
about
things wrong way
which just means stop thinking that they
are irritating from their own
side
okay and then you know if you're in a
really good class and you're having a
good time and your breakout group
happens to be really smart and not
irritating uh you can also slip in a
little
tenter you know you can
say which means in theory that uh if
your Spiritual Development reached a
certain place the very people that you
now see as irritating you might see as
Divine beings trying to help you I mean
and it wouldn't be forced you know it
wouldn't be like you know yeah they're
they're really a Divine being trying to
help me probably probably you know I
mean it's not like like that just boom
you know you're like wow they try to
help me I'm sorry you know and thank you
you know and and uh like that big
difference right one is a result of a
little study the second one is a result
of keeping your book you know just
refusing to collect Bad Karma and then
you're like wow Bo boom I'm surrounded
by these holy beings wow you know okay
number two you could stop that if you
stopped
uh the general
tendency of seeing things are
self-existent right the general
tendency of seeing things as
self-existent
which you which seems to have been
activated in our brains the moment we
were born or conceived it seems that
this is activated just by being
conceived you know boom you have it the
moment you're in your mother's womb
first moment of conception you have it
already which leads us to
assume that you'd have to
stop uh
if you can read you have that to stop
the seeds for that
tendency that came with you when you
were
born that were that were part of you
when you were born installed in the
factory factory
installed SE
right which all comes back to this I
mean it all comes back it comes to me it
comes down to
here right you stop number three this is
intellectual right this is intellectual
process this is the prita this is the
Perfection of wisdom Buddhism says that
you can get out of the disease through
sheer understanding you know like given
given choice of virtuous things to do in
a
day sincerely you should work on the
ones that that address your
understanding cuz that's where you can
break it I mean in the end the process
is an intellectual one and I don't mean
uh philosophers sitting around with
books and stuff like that I mean the raw
power of grasping that you made that
irritating person you know that's the
only thing that can save us the raw
power of understanding I think maybe
better than saying intellect the raw
power of grasping what's really going on
is the only thing that can save
us uh and that comes here so if you stop
the Habit you know every time you get in
a situation where someone's irritating
you if you just stop the habit of
thinking about them as coming from their
side then slowly you destroy these two
slowly you destroy these
two so gab J
says he covers this whole six steps in a
section called how how we get in trouble
corba say
[Music]
cor the steps by which we get stuck in
the self-perpetuating
cycle okay
samsar but he presents it in the section
where he's talking
about the Dharma Jewel and he's talking
about the sensation the truth of
sensation in the Dharma Jewel and the
part where he's not talking about Purity
Michael is talking
about achieved
Purity okay that's where these six steps
come up in the utar T that's why these
six steps come up the T I'll say it
again out he says these describe how we
get in trouble the steps by which we get
in trouble but he brings that up because
these are the steps that you have to
stop backwards way 65 4 3 2 1 right
in order to achieve
Purity which is half of half of the Dage
half of the truth of sensation which is
half of the Dharma jeel in your own mind
because the truth of the Dharma jeel
consist of the truth of sensation and
the truth of the path right I'm sorry so
yeah so really this is part of the truth
of
sensation sensation can be discussed in
terms of natural purity or a cheap
purity
and this is
obviously ACH achiev because you got to
go through these steps you got to go
first you have to do this then you have
to do that then you have to do that then
you have to do that then you have to do
that so now you guys know this being the
in-depth course where the six steps came
for course
12 and what was the other
course all I mean it gets in there
somewhere
right but we said it was a commentary on
the utar tant that it came from and now
you know why okay now you know how verse
12 this came from
the course 12 yeah this is where it
comes from this is where exactly where
and that's the context in which it comes
so it's really cool later when you teach
course 12 to people you know if you have
an extra day in South Africa right you
can say well you want to know where
those six came from and then you can
jump over to Tar Tantra and say this is
where they came from you know and that's
the verse where he bows down to the sun
you'll get the verse when you uh get the
reading I think you'll get a big stack
of readings when I get back in August I
mean the Tibetan already laid out but I
haven't uh had time to work on it
translate it but but now you know
exactly where the six steps come from
and you know the very verse it might be
fun when you get the reading to try to
suck it out of the verse the two last
two lines of the verse okay so that's a
extra job you have to do I think I check
I think I finished all though let me see
yeah and the meditation
assignment is everybody talking over
with somebody between
classes yeah it's something to do when
you're banging on things and like that
your
head okay meditation assignment 15
minutes Med analytical meditation think
of the one thing or person which gives
you the most trouble in your
life and how you might apply the six
steps just mentioned in stopping this
problem okay for me that's a real
natural
meditation yeah about and by the way
excuse me that's worldview I mean that's
why we call this whole organization
worldview that is worldview yeah that's
what you do my my book nowadays has
gotten down to plus blah blah blah minus
blah blah blah do worldview I just put
WV there's nothing else to do that's all
you have to do really
right what what are you going to say
well not that you said that no go ahead
so about step four you said it was okay
to dislike things but not okay to
dislike them
ignorantly or be irritated but if you're
disliking things then the theory is that
you can't be irritated if you dislike it
in intelligently impossible but do you
have to see emptiness directly no no
just a strong strong intellectual or you
or it couldn't be that you could achieve
a sensation for the lower Realms by
intellectual
understanding you can so that physical
irritation actually can go away just
through an intellectual Rel yeah I mean
when I was deep in the retreat it dawn
on me one day and I lost it since then
right but uh so many things but one was
that there's technically there's no
reason not to be joyful all the time
technically you know I mean I mean
technically there's no reason to be
less than very happy all the time
because it doesn't help anything it
doesn't do anything you know I mean it's
true that we live in a bad situation
it's true that we have things around us
all day that we'd rather not have around
us but but it's not true that there's
any benefit to being irritated by them
because then you can't think straight
and you might as well just be happy and
then you can deal with you can do the
opposite uh we have a thing we call
opposite day it comes from some movie
what it's a song Oh but there was also I
don't know some movie I don't know it's
just a day when you do the opposite of
what you want naturally do all day long
and if somebody for example were
hassling you you know or even um let's
say if you had problems in your group
with
divisiveness then um the only logical
thing to do would be be very happy and
never do that kind of thing yourself you
know like take extra steps to be um to
reach out to other people and other
groups uh and not be divisive rather
than going to the opposite party and
trying to talk them into either blah
blah or blah blah reconcile or
confront that's not the solution really
well partly the reconcile might do it if
you did it with wisdom if you said I'm
taking this step so that 6 months from
now don't see divisiveness you know and
you're not trying to work with hard
cement you know but going and trying to
talk to both parties is like hard cement
and don't expect a lot from that uh
unless you see it as applying to Future
Karma future Karma
yeah anyway that's worldview and to me I
mean that's that's Buddhism in a
nutshell that's all we have to do you
know uh stop rooc claing and start
gardening right okay hard to do easy to
[Music]
say you ready with this impress okay see
you
on yeah but someone what's on Saturday
we're gonna Saturday we're going to do
the
s
s yeah Micha the three qualities of
achiev Purity I've got three mate and
then with the other two possesses light
rays of wisdom and removing all
attachment intelligence senses are those
uh good
question if you really want to
know it's in the reading it's in the
reading let's just say it's in the
reading it is in the
reading okay
I thought I just unplug it yeah okay
here we go I'll read you the commentary
by put this back on I had this off
already you
know okay
uh the wisdom which perceives emptiness
directly
is unstained that's the first one right
in the sense that it's uh it's getting
free of certain seeds for
obstacles here's number
two people seeing emptiness directly are
possessed of the wisdom which perceives
emptiness directly those Sunray lights
sunrays
uh and G of J makes a point he
says I'm not just saying that the truth
of the path is the direct perception of
emptiness I also want to point out that
the jesi the wisdom of the hours after
that experience also in count for these
light rays the wisdom of the light rays
of the Sun the light rays of the sun
it's a metaphor yeah so that's number
two are they possess the wisdom ESS the
sun is possessed by Le like that yeah
yeah in the end then there's this huge
debate Michael if you want to get into
it are the light race separate from the
Sun are they coming out of the sun are
they I mean is the sun independent of
the light race or that's another
question
anyway in the end it's the wisdom which
perceives emptiness directly which
destroys the darkness right and that's
why he calls it the sun okay third one
this is this whole thing where it gets
in the six the six steps okay with
really the last one which was what oh
yeah it was
like you take all the objects in your
life like things you can see you you
have some feeling that they must be
pleasant or unpleasant from their own
side you are looking at them in the
wrong way you start to get attachment
like or dislike which is not a real like
or dislike is it and then if you took
the opposite of that which is thinking
them the right way that you've made
these things that irritate you right
then we could compare you to the son of
the Holy Dharma which destroys the
darkness that Li lies at the root of
ignorant liking and disliking and I
would bow down to that son if I were my
he says okay that's how he that's how he
glosses the three so the third one is
that whole stuff together yeah yeah
which is really beautiful so the six are
really in the third one
yeah okay cool
uh do
[Music]
pray fore
so the real trick is to uh you know you
got to be in this mood for the next few
months of uh thinking how do I present
this to a new person that walks in you
know like you don't want to dump all
this you don't want to overwhelm them
and uh that's the tendency for for
people who just got a big dose ofar
Tantra you know like you want to tell
them everything and you want to tell
them all the details and then they'll
just
glaze if they're new you know so you're
task for the next few months is to
really absorb this so well that you can
regurgitate it in a normal conversation
in normal
English uh in a way that would be easily
accessible to a normal person and that's
a big skill that's a very difficult
thing and uh you do a much greater
virtue if you convey it to them in a way
that they can absorb immediately than if
you give them all the details you know
it's good to have the details behind it
if they ask but uh you have to be in
this mode in the next few months of uh
like like I just go to bed at night or I
wake up in the morning I don't get out
of bed I just sit there and think how
would I tell this to a normal person you
know and then uh do that like you know
uh just before you fall to sleep think
how would I teach this this verse to a
normal person and then you'll be really
in the right mood when when it comes
time then the right things the right
words words will come and it may not at
all be like the technical presentation
of you know all the Sanskrit and toban
and bl okay